this video presentation is a little
discussion on how panarchy theory might
be useful to gain be and it comes in two
parts first we're going to look at some
ideas that hannah arendt had on the
human condition the basically the sum
total human action and we're going to
map that on to a notion of the
collective human action the sum total
collective human action is if we are
Martians looking down on humans as a
species that would be the first phase
then we're going to look at panicky
theory how it was developed by Buzz
Hollings
and see if we can then map the human the
model of human action onto the parity
theory in a useful way so hopefully
you'll enjoy the video and thanks for
asking the question
so Hannah Arendt wrote a book called
human action and it was the life the
life
Hana Arendt wrote a book called the
human condition it was the first volume
of a two volume series she was working
on she never finished she actually died
before she wrote the second book and the
second book was the life of the mind but
in this first book the human condition
she was looking at the life the
existential embodied life of humans from
deep history into the modern times and
she starts with a division of human
activity of the human and analysis of
the human condition that came out of the
early Greek times and their self
reflective process in their early
philosophy so it doesn't really matter
if in terms of this presentation if we
believe that these distinctions are
somehow metaphysically are ontologically
true the important thing is this is how
we have conceived of our human condition
over a long period of time from very
very early time so that itself
reflectively in acts the way we we act
in the world because we have this native
way of understanding our human condition
through epochs in our evolution and this
is what the Greeks knew or discovered or
observed about history of the human
condition up until their time so in her
Bull Connor Arendt
describes the three three domains of
human activity there's labor
there's work and there's action and what
distinguishes these are several key
features so first of all they
come into the human condition in time so
that labor is a more primitive or
primordial capacity work comes enters
into the human condition a little later
in time and then quite much later and
this was the discovery or the invention
of the Greeks this domain of human
action labor is the way that we take
care of our existentially biological
needs everybody is in a level playing
field with respect to labor it's that we
have to feed ourselves we have to find
shelter we reproduce ourselves and so
just like other animals Homo Labor ins
is the aspect of the human condition
which arises and falls from generation
to generation
it doesn't change each generation has to
feed itself each generation reproduces
each generation dies and so when we look
at ourselves from the activity of Labor
we imagine ourselves as all being equal
at some very primordial biological level
it's kind of leveling the playing field
and this is what Marx of course talked
about in terms of homo labor ins that an
hour's worth of work is an hour's worth
of work that at this very this is the
activity of the cognitive so calm you
terian aspect of labor that that defines
us as biological beings biological
animals and of course at some point in
our time with especially with you know
the Greeks understood and as we look at
the anthropological record as we
liberated human time and resources
through labor primarily by the free
labor of women in slaves then some men
and
that were men began to cultivate a new
type of human activity which is we can
just simply call work and unlike labor
where it's all the commentary and kind
of level playing field work was the kind
of activity that distinguished men
distinguished the great rhetorician and
have distinguished the poets and its
distinguished the architects who planned
the monuments so that the men that were
liberated into the capacity of work
would direct the laboring masses to
build the monuments so that we can see
that becoming a sage or becoming a
Emperor was the type of skill that
distinguished people's capacities and
not the kind of skill that everybody
just had in common so that this new type
of human activity became available
because of the excess resource of time
that was made possible by the great
laboring population and so work unlike
labor is not the goal of work is not to
just complete these cyclical
never-ending needs but to create
immortal projects that persist across
generations that create these memories
across across great swathes of time
these big projects and then the third
division that came later in our history
that the Greeks actually invented was
this notion of action and action the the
key feature of action or speech so
action was some kind of new way of
understanding our
and our capacities so action had to do
with showing up in the marketplace
showing up in the palace as a free
person and creating ideas in the
creative exchange of ideas and
democratization of the self
so in some sense similar to labor it was
extended to more and more the common
person and it was a capacity of free men
and eventually you know see this this
capacity of human action going into our
big great democracies today but action
was established on the fundamental
principle of the free self so you didn't
have to be quite as rare a talent you
just had to show up as a self in the
marketplace of ideas and the speech act
so actions was inherently political and
inherently depended upon recognizing the
other as equal to oneself and so then
this whole new way of manifesting the
human condition actually comes up in our
history quite late in the way from the
greats then when they got to this place
started to self-reflect and then there's
a lot of conversation around around this
obviously in the early Greek poleis the
men the slaves and the women who were
laborers were not quite as impressive as
the three people who were men of action
and speech and governance and ideas and
in between were the artists and the
artisans and the merchants and actually
the men of action the free men of that
spent their leisure time in the world of
ideas and governance and action actually
looked down upon the merchant class
because they couldn't understand why
they would occupy themselves with these
great works of genius because in that
sense they saw them
more like being laborers that they were
still tied to the physical or material
world so these are the three of the
tripe art division of the human
condition and so in 2009 I asked myself
what what how do these translates and
the sum total of human action if we
could just look at all the labor as one
dynamic system and all the workers
another dynamic system across all of
human species and action as another
dynamic system within the whole species
what would we see and to make a long
story short because I wrote long
torturous document explaining this
translation and why it works we could
map individual laborer that part of the
human condition as economies and so this
was very very clear to mark that that
Himalayans
was the driver of the great economic
systems throughout all of humans and you
know this is true for whether it's a
capitalist system or socialist system
it's where in the free economy we just
see an hour's worth of Labor's and hours
worth of labor that look at them
everyone as an independent agent this
kind of common quantifiable soup of
driving force and that the collective
sphere of work as a human condition
we're all our great technologies and
certainly technology has gotten so
advanced that we only you know we pretty
much in that technology the
technological realm in a collaborative
way
so unlike just the laborers who drive
the economy there are Steve Jobs of wool
who are in this category
and creating great impetus for
technological innovation we've seen this
has become a much more collective
pursuit than it used to be used to be
the you know the single Michelangelo and
Leonardo da Vinci's and now our
technological projects are quite large
and so unlike in the economy we just
want someone to show up this one man one
dollar one hour and just look at it
quantifiable and technology we want
people to show up as with skills we
suffer the idiosyncrasies of great
genius they do not want to level the
playing field we want novelty and genius
and so we see that both of these have
become great systems great economic
systems and great technological systems
and finally in the realm of the paulus
of action of speech acts
I call that collectively geo social
space because the way the key feature of
this is being able to show up as a
unique individual with a unique rights
with unique recognition you know and you
can you show up as other and you
represent your other nests in the
marketplace of ideas
I call it geo social space because in
many cases you know it started with
primarily identify with Geographic type
identities even if they're nation-state
that pretty much geographically
identified but increasingly these spaces
of identities are social spaces so that
and we see the collective explosion of
geo social space also over time so we
have many more identities than we we
used to have in terms of not necessarily
nation-states States but in terms of
affiliations and
categories and gender categories and all
murders and however and our friends on
Facebook and game B for example is a
emergent GL social space so the at least
an explosion of Geo social space in
different ways now the interesting thing
about economies is that the overall
trajectory of an economy is toward a
conservation of resources in a
hierarchical way so that we have more
fewer and fewer winners over time this
is true whether it's a communist
bureaucratic state or an authoritarian
state whatever what we call economies is
the human drive to build these larger
and larger aggregate or a cumulative
type of connections and so it is not
surprising then that the that labor as a
human condition has moved into a global
economy it is the end result of this
type of impulse in the human condition
whereas GL social spaces tend to
distribute novelty so there's more and
more identities going on over time now
what what's interesting is when for
example in the past when there's a lot
of tribal identities when a when statism
or nation ism comes through under an
economic policy globe you know connects
these than what you see here initially
is a loss of identity and you start
having for example these tribal
identities
into a single geo social spatial
identity of the nation nationhood and
that always comes in with a monetary
policy so that the thrust of an economic
impulse is this this hierarchical
synthesizing totalizing control of human
activity and the impulse of Geo social
space is the impulse for individuation
and more and more unique and identities
showing up more and more unique and
having your your uniqueness show up in
NGO social space so we see the post USSR
dissolution in too many nation-states as
the opening of Geo social space and the
current moves of the EU to create a
single monetary currency as the closing
of Geo social space and the increasing
of the economic impulse these are the
way these dynamics work and technology
is the increasing variation of forms in
order to express these things its
novelty its invention its innovation
into the physical world so they they
enable either economic the impulsive
economy to get more accumulative they
also enable the opening of Geo social
space of technologies are kind of like
drivers are both both of these impulses
so we can see the relative effect that
these have we can't if I turn them into
units of human actions so there are G
units there's units and there's T units
and so for example certain decisions can
increase G units and certain decisions
can increase B units and certain
decision can increase T units and I
started to see them as a natural
relations
that when one move the others would have
to move in this way and there's some
kind of natural antagonism between E and
G units and there is a feed-forward
aspect to T units and then one other
thing I did with playing with this is
that I looked at different societies
based upon the research that Don Beck
and the human emergence people did and
they have a whole theory of why the
different cultures are manifest the way
they do and it's a developmental theory
and my impression is is that these are
not developmentally driven but they're
their conditions by these three
different impulses in the human
condition so that for example we can
plot out just as a metaphor really the G
units and units and the T units and
three-dimensional space and we can
imagine societies let's say like an Arab
nation that has a very highly unified
economy and not a lot of novelty and geo
social space and relies only on a small
type of technology and that would be the
shape of that society and that in a
society that I would say gaining B is
looking for would have a lot of
potential for identifying and re
identifying and making up new identities
a distributed economy so it's not so
totalized and capturable but to some
extent we would probably need to be and
then they increase they're all driven by
increase in technological innovation so
they call this the shape of human action
and it can map on to all the different
cultural types in the examples
human emergence of stratification of
human democracy and my theory is is that
every society is is faced with
historical conditions and that they are
responding to those conditions by
sometimes having a cool or have a
revolution that increases the G units
and that creates more technology and
then there's periods where that creates
the accumulation of wealth which maybe
creates a more powerful state that
reduces the gene that's the shape is
always kind of pulling and pushing on
each other and that the sum total of
human action is the accommodation of
cultures for example this culture that
has this shape is also under adaptive
pressure from the other cultures and so
that that what how they accommodate
these three impulses dynamics of the
human collective human condition are
also part of the complete adaptation of
all humans now that were interconnected
so one of the things that is also
interesting about this is that just from
the way the culture of the society feels
under certain conditions whenever
there's fewer than in general whenever
there's fewer identities right so
everybody is more like you that you have
to work with and larger economic systems
so that you know there's there's a
natural hierarchy and you depend upon
the the banks are healthy so the
mortgage system is healthy and
everything is is kind of pushed toward
this direction so that there's stability
and a lot of resources built up
hierarchically and that the technology
is somehow
pacing itself then those are times when
the civilization feels more robust it
makes more sense we feel that things are
right there on target this is like the
typical 50s and 60s the that generation
growing up there wasn't a lot of
activity in Geo social space the economy
was accumulating resources in a
hierarchical way the trickle up kind of
economy the technology was moving to
FedEx that felt very sane and when
things were this way when the
predominant direction trajectories this
way toward a lot of change in technology
but that's technologically disruptive
and a lot of new identities like we have
today the corporations have the
identities there's many more gender
identities marriage identities
subsystems groups a lot of different
classes of ethnics ethnicity and culture
and those cultures are all hybrids of
other cultures well this feels less
robust and more chaotic but actually
this is when the system is becoming more
resilient because there's resilience in
this type a trajectory and even though
this feels more robust this is when the
trajectories in this direction the
economy is ready for collapse the the
suppressed identities are ready to
explode and the technology technological
imagination is just ready to exploit the
situation so whether the technology then
exploits the economy or those the new
identities creates the technology you
know this is an autopoietic system so
this is the first thing you need to
understand in the sense where I think
panarchy theory can come into the
conversation
game B so I just want to go to the
second slide and I will post a post with
this on game be some text about what
these three units and what what it feels
like to be in the situation's of
increasing G units or increasing units
increasing T units so that's the first
section
okay
so I said while I was writing that what
we were just talking about I started to
do more research and I came across a
book by buzz Hollings and buzz Hollings
tells the story was a biologist and he
was working on homo argument the
homeostasis of organisms the mechanisms
by which organisms stay homo static stay
in balance and he was trying to move
that concept into ecology because he was
an ecologist and that's where his
research was in ecology and he found out
that when you move the concept of
homeostasis to ecological systems that
didn't work and in fact homeostasis
homeostasis in an ecology was certain
death so he came very interested in this
and after many many years of research he
came up with what is actually happening
in ecological systems is much more
vibrant and he called it the panarchy
cycle so it's something similar to
chaotic systems and so he said basically
what happens in in ecology ecological
systems is there's four major phases in
a healthy ecology has to go through
these phases phases at a certain you
know turn over a certain number at a
certain pace in order to stay healthy
and so he for example we all know this
that the early management theory of
ecology actually destroyed a lot ecology
is because they were trying to optimize
for some kind of homeostatic condition
so he said there were four types of
drivers in this panarchy cycle and I'm
gonna tell the story because it's easier
to understand in terms of what's called
an island biogeography you know people
have studied where either new islands
have come up as just empty
no naked larva lava rocks and then
become established ecology ecological
communities over time and they also
studied this one like Mount Saint Helens
erupted and pretty much laid just the
ecology back to much more simple area
and they noticed that these go through
this you know notice that the evolution
of an ecology goes through that but this
can happen they've also seen this
happening over deep evolutionary time
and in all kinds of ecosystems so this
is what happens the after Mount st.
Helens that destroys everything the
first thing that happens is a
reorganization so this is called the
alpha phase where the conditions in the
in the low-cal start to reorganize some
plants move out some plants move in some
worms move out some worms move in some
some animals have died out so my other
animals have move in and sometimes
there's speciation happening here so
this is reorganization things are not
well connected because you know if it's
an island that has erupted out of the
ocean then there's a rat that you know a
couple of rats that have come off a ship
or a couple of pelicans ended up living
there you know so they're not there's a
lot of space there's not a lot in
connection and the situation's beginning
reorganized and then it comes down to
this phase of exploitation so once a
species gets a foothold then it starts
to really be successful and exploit its
niche and this starts to put pressure on
those species that are just barely
managing so some some of the species
some of these new emerging habitat
inhabitants start to exploit more nor
mitches and this will means that some of
the inhabitants leave or die off but it
also produces pressures to specie
emanate species then you have new types
that reorganize and exploit different
niches but eventually what happens is
that the new emergence of new species or
new types becomes crowded out and these
types of niches that can be exploited
become reduced and you have started to
get a dominant ecology so you might have
had like the old chestnut forests and
New England's that were not a lot of
species there was just kind of a
dominant ecology with all the biomass
all the energy gets stored and fewer and
fewer forms fewer viewer types of
activity and but there's a lot of
potential stored in there so this is
this is like the economy getting to to
be reliant on you know one monetary
system and a few big banks which is just
the 1% growing up here so this is the
level of case strategies or conservation
now the thing about this thing is that
if it grows too large if it doesn't turn
over fast enough and we'll get to why
that happens then there can be an
overshoot and there's a landscape
fitness thing happening so if it Oliver
shoots it can never come around and
regenerate itself but did the ecology
just completely fail fails and this was
the crisis of ecological management when
buzz Hollings was doing his research
because our interventions were all k
strategies kinds of
conserve what would it what is concerns
the forests in California conserve at
lands conserved the farmlands and what
happened is that created an overshoot in
the ecology in this conservation phase
in which those systems completely
collapsed because what HotList Polling's
realized that a healthy ecosystem had
this other it's called the backside of
the canopy cycle called the omega cycle
which is the daily cycle where this
phase of conserving more and more of
your resource potential energy and
kinetic energy and fuel and fuel forms
gets decomposed but you know fire and
the forest or periodic insect
infestation wetlands drying beavers
moving on so that this part that we that
management ecologic management was
seeing as destructive was actually a
semester in creative aspects of a
healthy ecology and so that was called
the release phase and then after release
then you get new types of species new
types of identities new participants
coming in new types of exploitation so
well what I started to see is that the
what we were looking at before the units
of human action actually could be mapped
on this now it gets a little confusing
because there are people that you know
obviously the first thing I say well
that this is like our economy you know
if if it moves too far up into where
there's only one monetary system and few
um few people on any money and without
that being decomposed or released back
into the system they distributed
and you don't have a viable economy so
there are people working with the
panarchy
scale to try to revise the economy but
here is where that idea is limited
because they're trying to revise the
economy but in the sum total of human
action the economies are just k
strategies they want to revise the
economies so that that yes they don't
want the economy to crash but the whole
notion of economy is that people you
know the this globalization of the
monetary system that it's hierarchical
and conservative in nature in nature so
people are using panarchy theory to fix
the economy are really only one of fixie
Congress really coming in you can be
more like if the economy is over time so
that that it can it can create more
mutual in the interdependencies among
larger and larger people over time so
that that and so that what what well you
can start to see if you understand this
that for a long long long time the only
decisions we make in our jail
politically and our political economy
are k strategies so we move from from
many different types of currencies we
move from a time where yes there was
been trouble you know there was death
accumulation and then there was a
mistake so that the economy could
recharge it and this the aspect that I
know your debt forgiveness this would be
designed for a release phase in the
economy but over time and that some
that's no surprise we have a global
economy that all our collective
positions have have become increasingly
more case strategies so k strategies are
the economic impulse the alpha strategy
the reorganization is the opening of Geo
social space
and the exploitation phase is what in
human action is technology so that we
can see and there's an interesting
relationship and the other slide the
relationship between K units G units
units and T units are in this case k
strategies alpha strategies and our
strategies is that that this overstreet
the ability for this to grow seems to be
increased by moving the dynamic here so
that that you if we see this in late
stage neoliberal capitalism yes that
creates more more than global
unification of monetary systems but it's
also being supported by the ability for
geo social space to be opened up and new
technologies to happen but there's a
kind of a delicate balance because if
there's an overshoot here than there
then the system will collapse so what we
see if we can overlay the units of human
action we see that moving in this
direction creates more resilience
anything that moves in this cycle based
strategies are always about previous
sense of safety or robustness although
we all know that there's a follow that
falling in that now but the question is
so now this is where this model can ask
interesting questions of game be in and
the question is this so we know how to
design for a Geo social space distribute
on that distributed identities more
fluidity and flexibility in the social
sphere more conversations more connect
you know more distributed networking
distributed networking is important
because of
not distributed networking and it's
underneath you know one company owns all
the distribution channels then that is
just increasing k strategies and we know
you know we're pretty good I'm getting
be about understanding technologies and
how to exploit technologies we
understand the jeopardy of this
monological focus on case strategies but
the question is how do you design for
you know can we and how do we design our
society our human condition for Omega
strategies so we know this becomes
resilient description ruthlessness and
after I read Nicholas Taleb I realized
that this that strategy is designing for
anti fragility now we're not talking
about designing so that the economy
could be anti fragile because that would
be kind of a you know snickering
ourselves because we don't want to
design anti fragile systems that will
only prejudice the conservation face of
k strategies we want to design for the
sum total human action to be anti
fragile so this is like the Greeks you
know the Greeks understood that we
labored that was an early activity human
condition and then they understood that
we had work and technology that came
next and then they invented this Geo
social space as part of the human
condition so the question is what is the
new domain of human action if human
action is an ecological system what we
want it to be or it's useful to think of
it that way
what is this domain a human action that
needs to be invented or discovered are
created that designs human action for
this release phase now they are very
interesting that's
very interesting question and it's I
can't say it's answered but I but I'm
beginning to suspect I mean you're still
doing research it has something to do
with how we conceptualize the different
type of social kids at the different
types of cues between what we consider
our society and what we consider in
ecology and I just give you a little
sense of that I can't answer the
question yet but for example for us and
you know so if we don't design for this
release the planet is going to design
for it eventually you know if we keep
going the plans are designed for the
release phase and so it's going to take
care of itself but the question is this
how can we be sensitive and partners
with that that part of the dance okay so
it has to do with this the this
conceptual limit in my opinion has to
this conceptual limitation we have
between what we take a societal cues and
what we take as an ecology it's up
figure-ground problem in a metaphysical
way so for example when what we see in
this release face of things like climate
change or the weather but the planet is
just doing something we see it as an
object even it has agency as the power
to kill us we see Ecology's as the
objective background against which we
make decisions so our labor our geo
social space and our technology as we
take social cues from that we we imagine
that as subjective space and what we say
use the term ecology for we imagine as
objective space and so we take different
types of cues from that all right and so
some of the answer in this
is moving beyond the dichotomy between
the kinds of cues we take in social
space as society from these three
aspects of human action and the kinds of
cues engagements or relationships we
have what with what we put in here as
ecology so what are our ecological
partners versus our societal problems
and and in that question I believe is
the answer to how to design with the
ecological or ecologic
partners to truly participate with our
ecological partners so that we are
intentionally doing the bad side of our
dance because the back side of a dance
if this is right it's going to come
anyways but we want to do that there's
that term that way Dalio used a
beautiful deleveraging
kind of a beautiful releasing of the
system so we know some aspects of
counteracting overshoot and the case
strategies for opening a Geo social
space more exploitation of technologies
but overall even with that the main
thrust is still basically to serve the
case strategy and so this is a coming
down here and understanding how to
design into or intentionally dance with
this release phase I think is a really
interesting question for game B and what
I like about it is that we don't have to
re-envision what an economy is that can
be part of our human condition we just
have to add a fourth term in the way
that the Greeks actually invented the
activity of Geo social space actively
invent our
with what we consider objective in
ecology in a way that solves this this
little puzzle